all right
[Music]
plant-based foods and the microbiome and
the preservation of health and
prevention of disease we have evidence
that high fiber plant-based diets can
prevent many different common diseases
maybe through the effect that these
diets have on the composition and
metabolic activity of our microbiome the
bacteria in our gut good gut bugs in our
colon eat the plant residues and spit
out Health promoting and cancer
suppressing metabolites like fiber is
metabolized to short chain fatty acids
which have profound anti-inflammatory
anti-cancer properties and we have
special fiber feeding microbes that chew
through the plant cell walls and release
all the anti-inflammatory antioxidant
anti-cancer goodies inside
so how many whole plant foods do we have
to eat
all the evidence points to a
physiological need for about 50 grams of
fiber a day which is what is contained
in the traditional African diet and is
associated with the prevention of common
Western chronic diseases this is up to
twice the recommended minimum and three
times the current intake in the United
States how can you prove the microbiome
is involved though fecal transplantation
stool transplants one man's trash
another man's treasure currently donor
fecal microbiota transplantation is the
optimum therapeutic approach for
recurrent clostridium difficile
infection C diff is today considered the
most common hospital acquired cause of
diarrhea it's a life-threatening
infection that can rear its ugly head
when your good gut bugs have been wiped
out by antibiotics so to get rid of it
all we need are more good gut bugs which
can be provided by a healthy donor
through the Fusion of a liquid
suspension of the donor's stool we are
winning with pooh
fecal transplants have proven their
worth in the management of recurrent C
diff diarrhea with cure rates up to 90
percent because of the success fecal
transplants have been suggested as a
potential treatment in other
gastrointestinal diseases for example
the inflammatory bowel disease known as
ulcerative colitis there have been four
randomized controlled trials and fecal
transplants appear to nearly double
clinical remission rates
but what about
non-gastrointestinal disorders
here's a case study of a series of fecal
transplants for multiple sclerosis the
patient experienced improvements in
their microbiome more of these
fiber-feeding anti-inflammatory bacteria
and there was a significant increase in
the levels of brain derived neurotrophic
factor which is suggested to play a
neural protective role in Ms as well as
both subjective and objective evidence
of improved walking which was the
patient's primary Ms symptom now to give
the new fiber feeder something to chew
on the patient was put on a high fiber
diet which is great but just putting
people on a plant-based diet alone may
help a stool transplants or not since
standard Western diets promote dysbiosis
a bad bug gut imbalance and neural
inflammation in Ms well plant-based High
fiberglasses decrease Ms risks
randomized placebo-controlled trials
will be needed to tease that out but in
the meanwhile we can certainly build up
good gut bugs the old-fashioned way by
eating fiber-rich whole plant Foods
what about fecal transplants for
depression interest in the gut
microbiome and its role in health has
exploded just in the last few years does
any of this have relevance in Psychiatry
maybe so several studies demonstrate
microbiome differences between depressed
persons and non-depressed persons and
after all an imbalance in
neurotransmitters is implicated in the
cause of depression and the gut
microbiome is known to synthesize large
quantities of these same neuroactive
supplements like serotonin and dopamine
and there's a major information highway
from the gut to the brain called the
vagus nerve that could potentially alter
mood States
early fecal transplants were delivered
from the bottom up through colonoscopy
but now we have crapsules
encapsulated feces to make it easier to
swap stool
here's a case report of a 79 year old
woman who suffered a tragedy and
subsequently lost her appetite became
introverted drowsing stayed in bed all
day wasting away 55 pounds over the next
six months she was hospitalized for
depression and prescribed multiple
antidepressant drugs but to no avail so
what the heck they stopped the drugs and
tried a fecal transplant the stool donor
was her own six-year-old great-grandson
who had a good appetite and outgoing
personality and a disciplinary stool I
don't even know what that means four
days after the fecal transplant she
started feeling better and by two weeks
she was frankly euphoric
she was able to go back home and within
six weeks all was back to normal
what about a fecal transplant for
bipolar disorder
the poor woman was in and out of Psych
hospitals with manic depression until
she got a fecal transplant with stool
from her husband that's romantic and
within six months she was symptom free
this case report was published in 2020
so symptom free for years no longer on
medication and has lost more than 70
pounds to boot either because she got
slim hubby stool or just being offer
psych meds she went from being
functionally disabled to running a small
business and is published two books what
about alcohol dependence alcoholism has
traditionally been considered
exclusively a brain disorder but hey all
these other psychiatric syndrome seem to
have links to the gut so they compared
the guts of Alcoholics to non-alcoholics
and they found that some
alcohol-dependent subjects developed got
leakiness which was associated with
higher alcohol cravings okay but maybe
instead of the gut issue somehow leading
to alcohol cravings the alcohol led to
the gut issues alcohol may have a Toxic
effect on the gut wall but both groups
were consuming the same amount of
alcohol at the time so maybe there is
some kind of gut connection after all
this was the study that blew people's
minds the transplant of feces from
alcoholics into mice induced in alcohol
preference these were mice without any
previous contact with alcohol all of a
sudden spontaneously preferring alcohol
and normally mice don't really like
alcohol but feed them some feces from an
alcoholic human and they do a 180 degree
switch
so wait are you saying that gut bugs can
determine alcohol cravings there's only
one way to find out and that's put it to
the test a randomized double-blind
clinical trial a fecal microbiota
transplant for alcohol use disorder
which is the current clinical term for
alcoholism they took alcoholics with
liver cirrhosis and active problem
drinking and randomized them to either
get a placebo enema or a fecal
transplant enema and within two weeks
alcohol cravings reduce significantly in
90 percent of the fecal transplant cases
versus just 30 percent of the placebo
cases and this was validated by p-tests
showing that they were drinking
significantly less too with improved
cognition and psychosocial quality of
life
now this is all still just experimental
and not without potential downsides yes
they're working on ways to make stool
transplants more palatable on balance
they've largely been found to be safe
though there have been cases of bad bugs
being transferred from donors even a
fatal case
and there's even a theoretical risk you
could be transplanted with cancer cells
making it the gift that keeps on giving
but in a bad way
foreign